Stanford University.
Let's talk more about conformal
mappings. These are very interesting in
their own
right. They are widely applicable to all
kinds of mathematical physics
problems. The most
direct is electrostatic problems.
Electrostatics problems in two
dimensions.
There are problems in theoretical
physics which are mathematically
equivalent to the electrostatic problem
in two dimensions. When I say
incidentally the electrostatic problem
in two dimensions, I don't mean that you
have particles charges moving in two
dimensions which interact with each
other with threedimensional kulom
forces. I mean particles which move
around electric charges which interact
with each other with mathematical
twodimensional kulom forces. Does
anybody know what the kom force between
particles is in two dimensions? One over
r one over r not one over r squ. How
about the potential energy between a
pair of particles?
You have to integrate logarithm.
Logarithm because the derivative of
logarithm is one over r. So in a world a
literal world where the lines of flux
can't escape out into the third
dimension which are really forced to lie
in the plane in such a world
electrostatics problems would have
um kulom forces which were 1 / r instead
of 1 / r 2 and the equations of
electrostatics would be two-dimensional
versions of the corres corresponding
equations in three dimensions. The what
are the equations of
electrostatics? Um let's let's just
write them down on the blackboard for a
moment. What do you describe an
electrostatics problem by? You describe
it of course by a electric field. But
there's something simpler than the
electric field. What is it? Electric
field is a vector. What's simpler than a
vector?
Well, charges but a scalar. A scalar.
The electrostatic potential. The
electrostatic potential which is
sometimes it goes under different
uh names but let's call it phi. What's
the connection between phi and the
electric
field? The gradient of phi is the
electric field. All right. So the
gradient of phi is the electric field.
And what's the equation for the electric
field in
electrostatics? Divergence of the
electric field is
the charge density, right? Charge
density on the right hand side call it
row. And we can rewrite that in terms of
phi by writing that it's I'll write this
out in detail in a moment. Del^ squari
equals
row. deli is e del equals row. So del^2
fi. And what does dell squared fi mean?
If we're in a two-dimensional world,
literally a two-dimensional world, let's
say with coordinates little x and little
y, then what is dell 2? Dell squ is the
second derivative of phi with respect to
x^2 plus the second derivative of phi
with respect to y^ 2. And that on the
right hand side is row. If there's
charge density, it's not zero. But if in
places where there is no charge density
in places where there is no charge
density it's just
zero you remember last time I think it
was last time we talked about this
equation and its
invariances conformal invariance. This
equation, this equation is invariant or
unchanged by any change in the
xycoordinates, any transformation to new
coordinates,
xycoordinates such that that
transformation is conformal. Conformal
means
angle preserving. In other words, that
when you make a transformation, when you
uh the angles, well, let's let's just
say the angles in the in the new
coordinate system are
perpendicular. Uh and that angles in the
new coordinates are exactly the same.
Angles between curves and new
coordinates are the same as between the
old coordinates. Conformal mappings.
Those are conformal mappings and they
are the kind of mappings that cgraphers
use in order to preserve the
shapes and the angles on a map. Although
they cannot in general preserve the
sizes of
things. Okay, so that's an example of a
place where conformal mappings occur.
Other places fluid flow in two
dimensions. These are also equations of
fluid flow. All kinds of problems at
least approximately are described by
um uh Lelass's equation. When the
leloian is zero, you have a standing
wave. No, no, these are not wave
equations. These are not wave equations
because they have a plus sign
there. These are electrostatic equations
and they don't describe wave motion.
You have to add if you want waves you
got to add in the T dependence. So this
is there's a there's a reason why we
call electrostatics
electrostatics because nothing is moving
right including the waves.
Then you have
uh is there a curl in two dimensions
also? There is a curl in two dimensions.
It's a good question. Uh let's come back
to it when well yes there is a curl in
two dimensions. The curl in two
dimensions is if you have a field like E
which has two components, let's say E
subX and E
suby, the curl only has one component.
In a two-dimensional world, the curl has
one D component and it is derivative of
EX with respect to Y minus the
derivative of EY with respect to X.
That's the component of the curl. could
think of it as the component of the curl
in the direction perpendicular to the
blackboard. But you know you can be in
two dimensional worlds where there is no
direction perpendicular to the
blackboard. So just think of it as the
curl the curl becomes a one component
object in uh kind of scalar
uh in uh in two
dimensions. It's only in three
dimensions that the curl is a vector. In
higher dimensions it's something else.
That's a two form but
uh okay let's uh let's talk a little bit
more about conformal mappings as I said
they are very interesting what they
allow you to do incidentally is from the
solution of a problem an electrostatics
problem for example
uh on some kind
of space some sort of space perhaps with
boundaries with some boundary
conditions. Uh you can derive an
infinite number of other
solutions with problems with other
boundary conditions just by mapping the
surface and uh taking the solution with
you and mapping the solution to a new
solution by conformal mapping. So as I
say there's all sorts of applications of
conformal mapping to electrostatics
problems. We're going to come back to
electrostatics tonight. at some
point. But let's talk more about
conformal
mappings. A conformal mapping is a
mapping of the plane, the xy plane or
the plane to
itself. So
here's a cartisian plane described by x
and
y. And let's use a complex coordinate
z= x + i y.
a
usual complex
plane or usual complex notation
representing the plane. Now we want to
do a mapping of the plane to itself or a
coordinate transformation of the plane.
Here's the W plane over
here. W is equal to U + I V. This is U
and this is V.
Incidentally, for obvious reasons, X is
called the real part of Z and Y is
called the imaginary part. Likewise for
U and
V. And a mapping from the X plane to the
W plane is just a rule given any point
in X and
Y assigned to it a unique and let's
assume the B mappings are one to one. In
other words, for every point on the x
plane, there is a unique point on the w
plane. And likewise, for each point in
the w plane, there is a unique point in
the x plane. That means any point
h did I say it wrong?
No, no, you know what I meant. For any
point on the w plane, there's a unique
point in the z plane. And for any point
in the z plane, there's a
unique.
Okay, this means you can take any
point and represent it either by
coordinates x and y or by coordinates u
and v and in that sense it's just a
coordinate
transformation. Uh u and v are functions
of x and y or you can say that w is a
function of z. So let's think of it and
vice versa but for the for today I'm
going to think of w as a function of z.
Given a point Z on the complex plane, it
uniquely picks out a point
W. These are complex functions. Both the
argument of a function Z and the
function itself W are complex numbers.
All right. Now, there is a calculus
of complex functions like
this called complex variable theory. And
uh let's just spend a few moments on it.
There's both an integral and a d and a
differential calculus, but we're going
to concentrate on the differential
calculus. Given a function w, we can try
to define a
derivative w of z. We can try to define
a unique derivative. And here's the way
we would do
it. Start at a point
z. And at every point Z, that
corresponds to some point over here
W. Let's move the point Z a little bit
to Z plus delta
Z. Here's
Z. And move the point to Z plus delta
Z. When you do so,
W will move to W plus delta W.
Here's W. Here's W plus delta
W. Okay. What is the derivative of W
with respect to Z at the point Z? Well,
the answer is obvious. It is delta
W divided by delta
Z in the limit that delta Z goes to
zero. usual logic of what a derivative
is. It's the difference between the
function at neighboring points divided
by the difference between the
coordinates at neighboring points.
There's only one problem, something new,
right? You can approach the point
Z from any
direction. And it's not at all clear
that in general even if the function is
nice and continuous and has all sorts of
good continuity properties. It's not
obvious that when you calculate the
ratio delta w by delta z and then shrink
the size of this that the answer will be
independent of which direction you're
coming in from. You might get one answer
if you come in from here. You might get
another answer if you come in from here.
You might get another answer if you come
in from here. So the question then is
what is the
condition if you want to have a nice
mathematical framework for complex
functions and you want to have the
notion of a unique derivative. Maybe
there is no good definition of the of
the derivative. But let's see what the
conditions are that the
derivative the limit of delta w over
delta z exists and is independent of
which direction you come in from. Now
I'm going to show you a sufficient
condition. You can go home and prove
it's a necessary
condition. It is a necessary condition.
Uh and it's almost as easy to prove as
what we will do. But I'll leave it for
you for
homework to prove uh what I'm going to
do is work out the necessary condition
by asking that the ratio delta w over
delta z is the same if you come in from
the x-axis along the x-axis or if you
come in along the y ais. In other words,
if your delta z is along the x axis or
along the y- axis that you get the same
answer. It is then not hard to prove
that if that's satisfied that no matter
what direction you come in from, you get
the same answer. So I'll do the simple
thing. You can do the slightly more
complicated. It's only a little bit of
algebra, but I I don't like doing too
much algebra on the
blackboard. Okay, let's
calculate delta W by delta
Z. Now, first of all, what is delta W? W
is U + I V. Well, let's let's let's not
be babies. Let's call it DW by
DZ. Whenever I teach PMEDs, I'm not
allowed to use calculus. And so, every
time there's a derivative, we call it
delta W by delta Z or whatever. And then
we're not officially using calculus, and
that's legal.
But then I secretly tell them, you
realize that's a derivative. Yeah. Yeah,
we
know. But I'm I'm always afraid if I use
it that they'll tell ombbudsman that I'm
using calculus in
class. Okay. So the change in W divided
by the change of Z. And what of course
is that? That's equal to the derivative
of or the change the small change in u
plus the small i times the small change
in v as you go from here to
here. derivative of the differential of
u + i v divided by the differential of x
+ i d
y. Okay, that's very
straightforward. Now let's calculate it.
If I come in along the x axis, if I come
in along the x axis, then dy is equal to
zero. Okay, dy is equal to zero if I
come in along the x- axis. And so this
must
equal coming in along the x axis, it
must equal du by dx plus i dv by dx.
Since we're keeping y fixed and not
varying y, this is the same as the
partial derivative of u with respect to
x plus i * the partial derivative of v
with respect to x. Oops. With respect to
x. Okay, is that clear?
Good. Now, let's come in along the y
ais. If I come in along the y ais, the x
is equal to zero. dy is not zero and the
partial derivatives are partial
derivatives with respect to y. So let's
see what that has to equal if under the
presumption that dw by dz doesn't depend
on which direction you come in from.
Okay, so let's see what we have to have
then we have to
have 1 / i. The 1 / i comes from the i.
The x is going to be zero. There's a 1
over i from the 1 over i multiplying dy.
And then we'll have partial of U with
respect to
Y. And then I over I will just give you
derivative of V with respect to
Y. U and V are real. I may I neglected
to say so. It may have been
obvious. U and V are real. It's W which
is complex. X and Y are real. Z is
complex. It's at least a necessary
condition. It happens to be sufficient
also. But it's at least a necessary
condition that this expression equals
this expression. Necessary for what?
Necessary that the derivative not depend
on which direction you're coming in
from. Okay. Now, so let's take the real
and imaginary part. Whenever you have an
equation that involves real and
imaginary parts, it really stands for
two equations. Equating the real part
and equating the the imaginary part. So
let's start with the real part. Here's a
real part that's got to equal
this. du by
dx must equal dv by
dy. And what about the other one? The
other one
says, let's see, that's the real part.
Here's the imaginary part. Let's put it
over here. I DV by DX
= 1 / I DU by
DY. D I DV by DX has to be 1 / I DU by
DY. That's equating the imaginary parts.
Let's multiply both sides by
I and use the fact that I squared is
minus1. So we get two equations. There
are two. They're not the same
incidentally. Look at them. One says du
by dx= dv by dy and the other says du by
dy equals dv by dx. No minus dv by dx.
One of them has a minus sign, the other
doesn't. If these equations are not
true, then the derivative doesn't exist
in a meaningful and unique way. If they
are both true, then the function w of z
has a derivative and the derivative is
well defined and the function is called
analytic. just a name when a function on
a complex function of a complex variable
has a unique derivative from every
direction it's called analytic at that
point if it's analytic if it's analytic
everywhere's then it's called entire all
sorts of names meomorphic holorphic I
never understood what they what they
meant holorphic is analytic now
meamorphic allows poles and uh
holomorphic is the same as analytic yeah
holmorphic is the same as analytic I
think that's I don't
remember. There's fancy names for
everything. I've learned recently that a
mapping which takes a point to a point
is called a bjection or something.
Well, we do dipomorphisms and all. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. These coordinate
transformations are difforphisms,
right? But all they are is coordinate
transformations.
nice smooth ones. Okay, so we have now
the the necessary and sufficient
conditions for a function to be analytic
every place where these are set. Now
let's look at these equations a little
more just for fun. See what they
say. They're coupled equations for U and
V. Can we uncouple them and write an
equation just for u and and an equation
just for v? Yes, we can. Here's the
trick. Um let's differentiate this
equation with respect to x. That gives
us d2 u by dx^2 the second partial
derivative with respect to x. And that's
equal to dv. That's equal to the second
derivative of v with respect to x with
respect to y. the mixed partial
derivative with respect to x and y.
Let's differentiate this one with
respect to y. That's d2 u by dy^
2. That's equal to
minus d2 v by dx by
dy. That's the same as that except for a
minus sign. So it follows that we can
eliminate it.
And one equation is d2
u by
dx^2
minus sorry is plus this is u. Yeah. No
no we just we have
just add them add them and the right
hand side will go away.
Well, that's a familiar
equation. That's just Lelass's equation
in two
dimensions.
So, a necessary condition. Well,
something looks a little like your curl
equation, too. It does. So, it's
something sort of curl free. That's this
one. Yeah, that sort of is. Is it is it
is it the derivative is curl free
in some sense? Yeah, one of them is curl
and the other is divergence depending on
which way you define the
components.
Uh yeah, if you think of u and v as
components of a vector actually you have
to think of u and minus v as the
components of a vector then what it says
is that the curl and the divergence of
the vector
vanishes. Okay, so that's that's this
equation. And if you do exactly the same
thing, we differentiate this one now
instead of with respect to x, we
differentiate it with respect to
y and differentiate this one with
respect to x. What we get is exactly the
same equation for
v. d2 v by
dx^2 plus dv by dy^2
= z.
So first of all, an analytic function w
of z contains two real solutions of the
lelass equation. That's interesting to
know. Every analytic function, every
function which has a
derivative and
incidentally most of the simple
functions that you write down, I I'll
give you some examples as we go along.
Most of the simple functions that you
would be likely to write down are
analytic.
So in this way you can generate a large
family of uh solutions of the lelass
equation. Now it's not sufficient to
have two solutions of the LLAS
equation. Two solutions of the applause
equation are just two solutions of the
LLAS equation. These equations link them
together.
So in fact uh it's not every pair of
lelass functions define an analytic
function really it's just one of them
and you can deduce the other one uh by a
trick but we don't need to go there.
Okay. So that's uh something
about
um these equations have a name.
Incidentally they were first to my
knowledge they were first discovered by
the mathematician Koshi and they're
called oh Koshi and Reman. I don't know
who discovered them first. Koshi and
Reman and they're called the Koshi
Reeman equations.
H yeah Koshi was first but sort of Reman
was more famous. Popularized by
Remon Koshi Reman.
Well, isn't that often how it goes? You
know, somebody's des Usually the first
guy doesn't get any credit, but
uh but in this case, Koshi was rather
famous mathematician and uh but not as
famous as Remon. So, physicists never
heard of him except in this context.
Yeah, in math he's got many other Oh,
yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But not as much
as Remon,
I don't think.
Tell me something else that Koshi did.
Koshi sequences.
I heard of that. He made calculus
rigorous. What's that? Made calculus
rigorous. That you don't get credit for.
Okay. Okay, the koshi reman equations
are each uh are related to lelass's
equation in this
way. Now I want to prove that these
mappings are conformal. That was the
whole point here that conformal mappings
are the same as these analytic
functions. Mappings or coordinate
transformations generated by analytic
functions. They are the same thing.
But let's just prove let's see how we
prove
that.
Um yeah let's uh let's just remind
ourselves one or two one small point
about complex uh
numbers. Let's suppose we have a complex
number. Let's uh so I'll call it Z. I'll
call it script Z here. Um it's meant to
be a small complex number but it doesn't
it doesn't need to be small but a small
complex
number but it doesn't need to be small
for this purpose. uh it can be
represented as x plus i y but it can
also be represented as another way in
polar
coordinates as a radius let's call it
row * e to the
i times an
angle that's another form of a complex
number now supposing we have two complex
numbers let's call this delta z because
I really do mean it to be a small little
displacement
Let's suppose I have another one. Let's
call it capital delta Z. Each one of
these are intended to be small
displacements, but for the moment
they're just complex numbers. And this
one is called row prime e to the i theta
prime. Think about the ratio of these
two. The ratio of these two delta Z over
delta
Z first of all has row over row
prime. We could make it simple and set
row and row prime to be equal and that's
because row and row prime are not the
issue here. What I'm interested in is
these
angles. What do I get for the angle? I
get e to the i theta minus theta prime.
Okay, the important thing here is that
the angle associated with a ratio is the
difference of
angles. If I have a ratio of two complex
numbers, the angular part of it is the
difference of the angles. Keep that in
mind. Okay. All right. Now, what we're
going to
do is um go back to the Z and W planes.
Here's the Z plane. Here's the W
plane. And let's
take starting at that point, let's
construct two little intervals. One of
them I'll call delta
Z. That's the same as this over here.
Incidentally, my script Z's and my
square Z's are the same
variable. Delta Z
and delta Z. We construct two of them
here.
there's an angle between them which is
the difference of the angles of the two
uh
uh variables themselves or the two
little intervals themselves. Now I can
map every point on this plane to a point
on this plane. In particular this point
here goes to
here. The end points also get
transformed. So little delta Z gets
mapped to little delta
W. You take the two end points and you
map them to here and that defines a
little delta W. Same likewise with
little delta
Z.
Okay. Sorry. Delta
big W. Delta
W. Good. Now what do we know? Assuming
it's an analytic mapping. In other
words, assuming that the Koshy reiman
equations are satisfied. Assuming that
the function is an the function W is an
analytic function. What we know is that
the derivative is well defined and
doesn't matter which direction you come
in along. What is the derivative if I
come in along the delta direction? If I
come in along the delta direction, it's
just delta w over delta z,
right? That's the
derivative. If I come in delta w / delta
z, but supposing I come along this
direction here, then what is the
derivative?
Big delta w. Big delta
w over big delta z.
Now if del if w is really an analytic
function it means that this ratio
doesn't depend on which direction you
come in along. So it says that these two
are
equal. The derivative is calculated
along the delta axis or the little delta
axis or the big delta axis should be the
same if they're analytic functions. We
can rewrite this. Let's multip uh let's
um let's multiply this by big delta z
and divide it by big delta w little
sorry little delta w we can write this
in another way it's big delta z divided
by little delta
z I've multiplied now I'm going to
divide by this one is equal to big delta
w over little delta
You everybody see what I
did? I put this one upstairs and this
one downstairs. That's all. But now what
does this say? This says the
ratio of big delta Z to little delta Z
is the same as the ratio of big delta W
to little delta W. What does that say
about the
angles here?
Let's call that angle theta and this
angle over
here. The angle associated with the
ratio is the difference of angles which
just means the
angle the angle associated with the
number where is
it? Delta Z over little delta Z is just
the angle between them. The angle
associated with big delta W over little
delta W is the angle between here. What
does this tell us? This tells us the
angles are
equal. In other words, the mapping is a
conformal mapping. Every angle on here
when you make the mapping maps to the
same angle on here. It doesn't say it
doesn't reorient. It says the angle
between curves. take any curve map it to
here and the angle that they intersect
at will be the same. That's the defining
property of a conformal
mapping. So the coordinate changes that
are associated with um with analytic
functions are exactly the coordinate
transformations which are the
invariances of lelass
equation or the coordinate
transformation that the lelass equation
doesn't change when you do those
coordinate transformations.
That's why in string theory, analytic
functions or coordinate or conformal
mappings are so
important because they're the invariance
of the uh of the equations of motion of
a
string. Okay, let's let's do a couple of
examples. I'm going to show you two
interesting examples.
Well, let's first check a couple of
simple functions and see if it's really
true that
uh uh let's take Z= X Z uh W= Z ^2.
That's a real easy one.
W= Z
^2. Let's check if it's analytic. Okay.
Um Z is X plus I Y.
X + I Y^2 is equal to X^2 - Y^2 +
IXY and this must be equal to U + I
V. W is equal to Z ^2. All right. So
first of all, what is
U? U is equal to X^2 - Y^2. The real
part of this side is the same as the
real part of this side. So that's X^2 -
Y^2.
What about V?
XY. Just 2XY.
There's a square missing in the Yeah,
good. Right. That's what you meant,
right? Okay. Let's check whether these
satisfy Lelass's
equations. Lelass's equations say that
the second derivative of u with respect
to x^2, what is
that? The second derivative of u with
respect to
x^2 is
two. Second derivative two. Second
derivative of u with respect to
y^2 minus 2. So second of u with respect
to x^2 plus second derivative y^2 is
zero. Okay. What about um second
derivative of u with respect to x x^2
zero? If you differentiate it once, you
get y and then you can't differentiate
it with x again. Likewise, second
derivative, this one also is a good
solution of lelass's equation. All
right.
Now, that proves that every function
that you'd ever be likely to write down
is analytic.
Let's write one down. Let's write one
down which is not analytic. Okay. Um h
one over Z. Well, that's that only fails
to be analytic at one lousy point. So,
let's not worry about that. Um no, let's
let's make a really bad
one. First of all, W equals Z. That's
that's very analytic. That's that's a
very that's a very simple one. But what
about W equals complex conjugate of
Z? W= complex conjugate. Remember what a
complex conjugate is? You reverse the
sign of the I. This would say that
W is equal to X - I
Y or U is equal to X and V is equal to
minus Y.
I will leave it to you to prove that the
that the uh Koshy rearm equations don't
work. I'm not going to do it. You do it.
You get a wrong
sign.
Uh you can see you couldn't possibly get
the right sign for both plus and minus.
One of them would say u= x v= y and the
other says v= x v= minus y. Can't both
satisfy the koshi reman equations. I'll
leave it to you. I don't want to do it
now.
Um, I can't. That's because I can't
remember the Koshi Reman equations. Oh,
there they are. du by dxals dv by dy.
Nah, the minus sign gets in the way,
right? So, the answer is
no.
Okay.
But analytic functions are written
without ever invoking the complex
conjugate. Complex conjugates are not
analytic
functions. W= Z W= Z ^2 W= Z cubed. W= Z
to any power is an analytic
function. Let's do another one for fun.
Let's do W= log. Oh, let's let's No,
let's do uh
um Yeah, let me see what I was going to
do.
Yeah. W equals no Z
= E to the W. Let's do W= E to the
Z. That's a more complicated thing.
Let's just check it and see that it's
really
analytic. You can also do logarithm. We
don't have to do both logarithm and
exponential. Why is that?
One is the inverse of the other. Um if
we come back, how do we know that if a
function is analytic that the inverse of
it is
analytic match the angles have to match
going one way, they have to match the
other way. If the angles are preserved
one way, they have to be preserved in
reverse. Exactly. If the angles are
equal going one way, they have to be
equal going the other way. So,
uh, it's also true that derivatives of
inverse functions are just one over the
derivatives of the functions themselves.
And so, if they're independent of which
way you come in, still true. Okay, but
let's try uh w equals just to just to
learn the experiment around and to
unrust your uh your use of uh complex
numbers. All right. So W then is U plus
I V,
right? What is E to the Z? E to the Z is
E to the X + I
Y. All right. E to the X plus E plus I Y
is the same as E to the X which is real.
E to the X is real. And what about E to
the I Y? Is there another way to write E
to the I Y?
cosine of y + i sin of
y cosine of y plus i sin of
y. Okay. So, can you read off u from
this? U is equal to let's put it up
here. U is equal to E to X
* cossine
Y and V is equal to E to X * sin of
Y. Should we check the co K cohy remon
equations? Let's check them. d u by dx.
What is du by
dx? What happens when you differentiate
e to the x with respect to x?
Okay, you get u again. So d u by dx is
same thing. d u by
dx is equal to e to x cosine y. What
about dv by
dy? All right. What do we get when we
differentiate this with respect to
y derivative of s is
cosine? Okay. So this is again equal to
e to the
x cosine
y. Yeah. So the first koshi equation is
correct and you can check the other one.
It's also correct. All right. So we
check that e to the z is a good analytic
function.
Sums of analytic functions are sum are
analytic. Ratios of analytic functions
are analytic except at points where the
denominator
vanishes. At points where the
denominator vanishes, something is
infinite and
uh and uh that those are nasty points
where everything breaks
down. Okay, let's take I took wals e to
the z. Let's take W= logarithm of
Z. That's the inverse function. W=
logarithm of
Z. And let's see if we can see how this
mapping works. This is an important
mapping in string
theory. W equals logarithm of Z. Let's
see if we can see how it works. In
particular, I'm going to apply this
mapping to the half plane. The half
plane now means take the half plane
which has a
boundary. It's the half plane to the
right. I'm not going to it's not mark
it. We're interested in the half plane
to the right here. Here's the
origin. And let's see if we can see when
we do the mapping where the points of
the half plane go. Here's the W plane.
This is the Z
plane and here's the W
plane.
Okay, first of all, what about the
origin of the Z plane? What happens to
the origin of the Z
plane? The origin of the Z plane goes to
logarithm of zero. Where is logarithm of
zero?
logarithm of zero is of course not a
number but we can take logarithm of a
tiny tiny tiny number and the logarithm
of a tiny number is a very negative
number. So this point out here maps to
some place out at infinity way off to
the left
here. Right? Let's not try to figure out
exactly where it goes because it doesn't
go anywhere really. It goes out to minus
infinity.
Uh what
about logarithm of plus
infinity? That's way out
here. Okay, but that's not very
illuminating. Let's take let's take this
plane and write it in the other form. Z
is equal to R E to the I
theta. Then what is this half line down
here? That's the line theta equals what?
Theta = - /
2. Here is theta = + /
2. Here is e to the i theta. What is the
logarithm of r e to the i theta?
logarithm of r e to the i theta is log
of
r log of z is equal to logarithm of r
plus i
theta plus i
theta. So where does a general point go?
It goes to some real number plus i
theta. And what does theta go between?
Theta goes from minus p / 2 to plus
p / 2. Here's minus p /
2. Well, theta equals minus is i theta
is minus i pi /
2 - i pi / 2. And the upper end here
goes
to plus i pi /
2. An infinite line. In other words,
this infinite line here gets mapped to
this infinite line and this infinite the
infinite half line and the other
infinite halfline gets mapped down to
here. The origin being way out here. So
what we've done is we've taken this
whole space and we've kind of bent the
axes and squashed the whole space on a
narrow ribbon. The ribbon between minus
i pi / 2 and plus i pi /
2. Okay, we could draw some curves to
see if we can see what's going on. We
could first draw some straight lines
like this. The straight lines coming out
of the origin here, they have to go to
the origin. They also have to go out to
infinity. And those lines map to
straight lines like
this. It just bands at constant
angle. A constant
angle. Okay. Next, what about the radial
circles which look like this? Where do
they go?
vertical
lines. Why is this strip description
interesting from the point of view of
string
theory? This was the way I described the
world sheet of a string in terms of a
coordinate. What do we call it? Sigma.
Sigma which went from minus pi over two
to pi / 2. That was if you like the
parameter along the
string and the other direction
was the time
direction. This was the world sheet of a
string where the string went from minus
p /2 to p /2 in the
coordinates and swept out time
uniformly. Everything was
translationally invariant in time. No
special time. And you can see from this
picture here that everything has a nice
symmetry along this
axis. How does the symmetry along this
axis? Let's say we push everything to
the left. What happens
here on the Z plane? Let's take the W
plane and shift everything to the left.
What happens?
It
shrinks. It shrinks by a uniform factor.
If you push to the left a certain
amount, it shrinks by a uniform factor.
If you push to the right, it expands. So
these are called dilations. Dilations
are transformations which expand and
contract. They transform into the time
translations. Curious? All right. This
is one mapping which is of interest.
This means that the string world sheet
could be described as living on a half
plane like that with the incoming string
coming in at that point right there
being injected in right there. The
incoming string at a time in the remote
past can be thought of as being injected
onto the world sheet right at this
point. Let's do another mapping.
I got a quick question for you. So
you've let R equal to be one. Is that
it? No, no, no. Uh no no r= 1 is some
particular line here. These lines are
lines of constant
r= 1 is right at the center here. No, I
did not. Yeah. R is those circles. R is
those circles that you Yeah. R are the
various circles here. This is r equals
0, r= 1, r= 2, r= 3. Uh, sorry, r is not
r is not zero over here, but r is zero
out there. If I can clarify, I can to
say that the left one is like polar
coordinates, but on the right, it's not
polar coordinates. It's the old xy
coordinates. Yeah, but it's a mapping
from one to the other. It's a mapping
from one to the other. And the one thing
you can be sure of is that angles on
here when they map to here they cross at
the same angle. That means among other
things that if if the LLAS equation for
X now being X of uh the X coordinate of
the string. If the LLAS equation is
satisfied for a field for a degree of
freedom living on here, it's also
satisfied on here.
So that's the uh that's the symmetry of
string theory. You
can stretch
deform the coordinate space to fit
whatever particular reason you may want
for redrawing it. Here's another
form, another mapping of the half
plane. Oh, before I do
that, let me tell you what
happens if you map the whole plane by
the same transformation.
If you map the whole plane from the same
trans or over the same transformation,
the angle goes from minus / 2 to
what? Minus p / 2 + 2
pi. All right. We could also let it go,
let's see, we could also let it go from
uh let's
uh Yeah. Okay. It goes from minus p
/ 2 to minus p / 2 plus 2
pi. 2 pi is up. Add 2 pi and it becomes
a fatter
strip. But there's something new. What's
new? What's what's different about this
strip than the original strip?
It wraps around. Yeah. No. When you go
all the ways around the angular
direction, you come back to the same
point. That means starting here when you
go all the ways around you come back to
the same thing. In other words, what
happens if you map the whole plane? What
do you get?
Cylinder.
Cylinder. Not a Taurus. Because this end
is not identified with this end, but the
top is identified with the bottom. You
get a cylinder.
Yeah, it's a cylinder. An infinite
cylinder. This is the space that you
would use to describe an open string
with two ends. How about this one?
Closed string. Right? So it's natural to
think of well open strings you can
describe on the half plane closed
strings on the whole plane with no with
no
boundaries. Okay that's a uh
that's useful mathematical uh fact. Now
let's come to another
mapping. Let's take the Let's forget
this W plane and map to another W
plane. Different
mapping. We're starting again with the
same Z
plane, X, Y, and so
forth. How about this one? W
= Z + 1 / Z minus
one. Let's see if we can see where it
goes. Is that what I want?
Let's see.
Um, or do I want Z = W + 1 over W minus
one? One or the other.
Um, let's try it. Let's see if we can
see what it
does. Z equals 0. Where does Z equals 0
go?
minus one, right? When Z is equal to W,
I'm sorry. When Z is equal to zero, W
goes to minus1. Here's the W plane. W
goes to minus1.
How about when Z is equal
to ah when Z is equal to infinity way
out here
W goes to one
Z is equal to infinity or in other words
when Z is very very large
goes to one it goes to plus
How about
when Z is pure imaginary up
here? When it's pure imaginary, in other
words, when it lies on the boundary of
the half
plane, where does it go? That means that
Z is equal to some real number time I.
R* I. What happens to W? W
becomes 1 +
iir over 1us iir I think with a minus
sign. How about 1 + iir over 1 - i?
Anything special about
that? Magnitude one. Right? Magnitude
one. The sums of the squares of the real
and imaginary parts are the same. So the
ratio of these two has magnitude one. So
where is this upper half line here? It
lies on a unit circle. It lies on the
unit circle because it has magnitude
one. How about the lower half line here?
It also lies on the unit circle.
So when x varies over the entire half
plane
here w not x but when z varies over the
entire half plane
w v varies over the
unit disc is called a disk over the unit
disk. What what is this useful for?
Well, in practice, it is useful for
solving Lelass's equation in various
contexts. Uh, you put in various
charges, for example, in various places
and you want to calculate the electric
field. If you can do it in this
geometry, then you can transform the
same problem to this geometry and solve
a whole slew of problems.
So one of the things this is good for is
mapping back and forth electrostatics
problems and it is used that way uh
quite
frequently. Let's see let's uh do one
other thing before we finish. We not
before we finish but before we finish
with this we started with these circles
and these lines
here. What do they look like on the unit
disc here? Well they look roughly like
this.
The radial
lines start at one end and go out to
infinity, but infinity was over here. So
the radial lines look like this. They're
actually circles. They they actually are
circles. Circles of different radi.
And the lines of constant radius here,
they look like
this. And they bunch up as you get
closer and closer to
the Do you remember the transformations
on the ribbon here? There were
transformations on the ribbon which
moved which translated the ribbon back
and forth in this direction. They
corresponded to dilotations or
dilations, expansions and contractions
here. They correspond to some
complicated kind of motions here.
When you said that those arcs that you
drew are circles, they're circles in the
the plane circle. They're circles, but
their centers are in various places. I
mean, this one is not a circle. Clearly,
it's a straight line, but it's the limit
of a circle. This one is a circle with a
center way down here. This one has its
center somewhere here. This one has its
center somewhere here. And of course,
this one has its center right over here.
So would cgraphers like that
transformation kind of looks like Well,
of course that's not a sphere. It's a
it's a disc. Yeah, don't don't confuse
it with a sphere. Now, if you did the
same thing with the full plane, you
would get a sphere, but uh that's I
didn't want to do that. Now,
the optical illusion anyway, those are
circles on a sphere. Yeah, it looks like
a sphere, but it's not intended to be a
sphere. It's just intended to be a
mapping from the plane to the
disc. All right, so we have now another
representation of the
same picture.
The left half plane goes to the outside
of the
disc. Left half plane, right half plane
is here. That's the inside of the disc.
The left half plane goes to the outside
of the disc. It didn't disappear. It
just went to the outside of the disc.
H I don't know who answer asked the
question. It's a sphere because when you
take the limits, things go
around, right? You mean when you take
the full plane? The full plane, it's a
it's a little bit complicated. It's a
stereographic mapping of a sphere. I
think there's a single point at infinity
and there's a mapping direct
and it can be mapped stereographically
here.
Which was the radials? H the radials on
the left the spokes going out. Which
which set of curves should they go? The
spokes going out here. They begin at
this point. This point is that point.
infinity. Let's see. Z equals infinity.
That's W = 1. That's over here. So every
one of these lines, let's take the one
which is first of all completely
symmetric between the upper half plane
and the lower half plane. That's the X-
axis. The X- axis, that's just this
line.
Okay. The radial lines above the axis
above the X- axis are like that.
Radial lines below the x- axis are like
that.
Okay. Then there's the circles on
here. Here's a circle. Every one of
these circles sort of surrounds this
point here. Sort of half surrounds
it. They start well let's see. They
start on the boundary.
They surround this point and they come
back to the boundary. So they start on
the boundary of the disc. They go around
and they come
back. But as you move
out, they go like
that. They sort of get turned a little
bit inside out as you go from here to
here. So that their curvature is in the
opposite direction. Are they circles
too? Yeah. Yeah, they are also
circles. It's an interesting fact under
these mappings uh well under under this
mapping under this kind of mapping this
is called a linear fractional mapping.
It's linear it's a fraction made out of
two linear functions. Under linear
fractional mappings the collection of
circles and lines transform into the
collection of circles and lines. So
here's a
line. It transformed to a circle.
Uh here's a
line. It transformed to a certain
circle. Circles and lines transform the
the collection of circles plus lines
transformed to circles plus lines. Not
under every conformal mapping under
linear fractional transformations. And
that's what these are called. Sometimes
called meious transformations. And they
have nothing to do with meous strips. At
least I don't think they do. Say meas
though.
Okay, let's take a break for uh for five
minutes or so. What about that point at
halfway infinity? The point where the
point at halfway infinity is a straight
line. The point at halfway infinity.
What is it? Basketball.
What is halfway infinity? Isn't that
Isn't that straight line in the vertical
line in the middle there? That one?
Yeah, that's uh that's some particular
radius. Probably radius one. I'm not
sure.
Let's see. It goes through the point. It
goes through the origin. Yeah,
it passes through the origin on the W
plane. So, where is the origin on the W
plane? It's the thing whose logarithm is
zero. One.
Right now, I'm going to try to give
you
a fairly complete definition of what
string theory
is. We've set up a lot of the
mathematics. The problem, of course, is
proving that these things work in
detail. And that of course is where the
real difficult stuff comes
in. But
um let's go back. You may recall that we
uh talked a little bit about what
scattering amplitudes look
like and how you derive them in string
theory. We started with a simple
example where two particles collided
came in and two particles went
out. We said okay let's just
take the world sheet of the whole
process to be a infinite strip like
this. But since two particles are coming
in let's slit it down the middle like
that. Two particles are going to go out.
Time goes from left to
right. Two strings come in, two strings
go
out. So, here's the two initial strings.
I I don't want to draw on this, at least
not with
black. Here's the incoming string, and
it propagates. Here's the other incoming
string, and it propagates. The two
strings
join, form a single
string. Here it is in here.
And then after a period of time, how
much time? The answer is you integrate
over the time. As in quantum mechanics,
you always integrate over all possible
paths from beginning to
end. In other words, you sum up the
amplitudes for all possible histories
and then the end what goes out is two
strings.
Again, what do you calculate? I'll
remind you what you calculate. Um, well,
we talked about it in several different
versions, but in one version, you think
of a path integral. And the path
integral, the degrees of freedom are the
coordinate positions. We could define a
sigma variable and a tow variable or two
coordinates on this two
um coordinates on this world sheet. for
the degrees of freedom of the space-time
positions, the space-time coordinates of
a point on the world
sheet. So, what are they? They're x
mu where mu goes from one or from zero
zero being time. What's the uh last
one? 25 if it's in 26 dimensions, nine
if it's in 10 dimensions.
But whatever the collection of
coordinates are that describe the
location of a point on the string and we
call that x mu
of sigma and toao. Let's say sigma and
tao could be the two coordinates on this
world sheet. They're of course the same
as these little x's and y's here.
They're the coordinates in a
two-dimensional
space. And those co the the sigma and
toao are the x's are coordinates in real
spaceime. The sigma and toao are just
labels which label points on the world
sheet. The x's are their real space-time
location. And if I know the space-time
location of every point on the world
sheet, then I know how the world sheet
is uh spread out over
space. What do you do? We calculate a
certain path integral. And the path
integral that we
calculate is
e to the
minus the
action. We did a little trick. I'm just
reminding you now of a trick. We did a
little trick of letting tow go to i tow
in order to get rid of various factors
of i. We talked about it. I'm not going
to do it over again. And there was an
action. The action was the integral over
d sigma and d
tow of what? It was dx
mu d to
squar minus the x
mu d sigma squ plus plus the x mu d
sigma
squar. What exactly does this mean? The
x mu by dau^ squar means the sum of 26
terms. The x1 by da squ the x2 by da squ
the x3 up to the last one. That's what
these things mean. This is the
exponential of the
action. And what do we do with it? We
integrate
it path integral over all possible ways
of filling up the surface. It's often
written delta x of sigma and
toao. This means path integral and it
means integrated or sum it up over all
possible configurations of the uh of the
world sheet in spaceime. The way the
world sheet fills up
spaceime. But how does this formula here
first of all how does this formula know
about the momenta of the incoming
particles?
The momenta of the incoming particles we
have to add in by hand. And it's
inconvenient in this picture to to say
how we do it. I'm going to tell you in
another picture exactly how we do it.
But for the moment, let's just suppose
somehow we have put in the momenta of
the incoming and outgoing
particles. There somehow embed in this
calculation and we integrate over all
x's. Now there's one more thing. What
about the time interval between here and
here? We integrate over
it. All right. So, what we're doing in
effect is summing up all possible ways,
all possible histories of these two
particles oscillating, then forming a
single particle, and then forming two
particles again. All possible histories,
all possible ways that the world sheet
fluctuates.
That's this integral over here. It's an
integral of the action and it's a
complicated thing and we haven't even
yet put in the uh the rule. I'm going to
tell you what the rule is for the
external particles in a moment. But
before we do
it, what did we call this? We had a name
for this uh picture.
What was it? The sports band. Oh, the
sports band-aid. Yeah. Yeah, the sports
band-aid. Right. Butterfly bandage or
whatever it's called. Right. Well, now
we can make use of our freedom to map
this picture to
other sets of
coordinates for the world sheet.
Conformal mappings. Conformal mappings
is a very wide variety of analytic
functions and in fact the variety is so
large that you can basically map here's
a this thing has one boundary. The
boundary goes from here to here. Now out
at infinity here, what goes on in
infinity is is subtle. But let's jump to
to this boundary. It goes all the ways
around one just like the sports bandage
goes around once. It has one boundary
apart from the fact that little pieces
of the boundary are off at infinity.
We'll worry about that later. You can
map anything with one boundary like that
to anything else with one boundary by a
conformal mapping. In particular, if you
so choose, just for symmetry, you can
map this whole world sheet to a circle
or to a disc. Exactly the same disc. I
showed you how to map a single strip to
a disc. I didn't show you how to map the
sports band-aid to a uh to a disc. It's
a little more complicated. I once
figured it out many years ago. I worked
out the mapping in detail.
or remember
it, but you can map it to a
disk. And then where are the incoming
particles? Those are points on the
boundary. The outgoing particles are
also points on the
boundary. Let's draw some lines to just
indicate uh how this
looks. So if we draw some vertical lines
here, some vertical lines here, they
will look like
this. Notice that these vertical lines
over here surround the point at infinity
here. That's this one. And then all of a
sudden
they come together like that. That's
this point. Then they go like this.
That's what the mapping from here to
here looks like. The horizontal
lines, I don't know, they
go, they're a little more
complicated. That's what it looks
like. The point is you can do exact. You
don't need to know where these lines
are. Incidentally, if you can forget
where they are, they don't play any
special
role. The point where they split and
join in this diagram here is determined
by the
position the positions of the uh of
these external points here. As you move
them around, these points move closer
and farther apart. When you move these
points together this way, these points
get very far apart. When you move them
together horizontally, these points move
together. So the same picture, the same
uh physics, different
pictures. All right. What do you do
here? You do exactly the same
thing. You take the x by dao squared.
You could now call it uh you could now
call these coordinates by different
names if you like. You could call them x
and y or u and v doesn't matter that
toao and sigma coordinates. You
calculate exactly the same quantity
integrated over
here. But now I can tell you what you do
with the external particles. You have a
rule for each external
particle one more factor in the
integrant. Anybody know what that factor
is?
It's the thing which injects momentum.
Uh delta function of
what?
Okay. X's are integration
variables. K's are the momenta. K1,
K2, K3,
K4. These are the momenta coming in and
going out. You put in for each external
particle. So each particle coming in,
you put in a factor into the integrant
here
of e to the i k
x at the
position let's call this point
z a product for each external particle.
One more thing goes in. It's a factor of
e to the i kx where k is the momentum of
the particular particle that's coming
in. So you have an e to the i kx1 and
they're on the boundary. They correspond
to particles being injected into the
diagram like
that. That
rule comes from quantum mechanics. It
comes from well we could talk we can
discuss this rule another time. I wanted
to lay out the whole set of rules. You
do a path
integral over all possible embeddings of
the world sheet into
spaceime. All possible ways that this
world sheet can be embedded in
spacetime. E to an
action and for each external particle an
E to the I K X where the X is at the
point where the insertion of that
particle happened on the world sheet
here. Z here corresponds to the
coordinates of this point on the plane
here. One last thing after you're
finished you have to integrate over the
positions of these insertions.
That's it. That's the whole story. That
that is what string theory is. This is
open string
theory. That's uh that's the whole set
of rules. A a path integral a path
integral over all world sheets, all
embeddings. You can describe it on a
dis. You can describe it on a sports
bandage. You could describe it however
you like. What did you get after you
finished all this integration? The
scattering amplitude.
The scattering amplitude for a particle
of momentum K1 K2 to become K3 and K4.
But if those are fixed, how come we
integrated over them? The moment or the
position momenta? The momenta. No, we
didn't integrate over the momenta. we
integrate over the locations on the
visia
of those of the insertions.
Okay. So those don't represent the
actual values. They just represent where
they are. Those points they they replace
the integration over the separation,
right? Okay. So it doesn't So those
those are fixed. Those are bound. Those
are not fixed. No, I mean the K1 2 3 4
are the K's are fixed. The K's are the
momenta of the particles coming in and
going out. So we get the basically the
scattering amplitude, right? Scattering
amplitude for a particle of momentum one
and two to become a particle of momentum
minus K3 and minus
K4. Remember all all momenta are carry
are is that product multiplied by the
whole integral? It's inside the
integral. Inside the inside the integral
is that that you call that the action.
This is the action and that's part of
the action. This is no this is these are
called vertex
operators. The vert vertex operators
mean they just bring some they just
deposit momentum into the
uh into the diagram.
So they inject the flow of momentum into
the diagram. We'll work that out another
time and see where this the question is
are do they go inside the upper
integral? Yeah, they go inside the
integrals.
Not in not inside this integral. No, not
inside that integral.
No, we could write it out. Let's write
it out more
clearly. Integral over all
possible well, let's see, integral path
integral. Let's just call it path
integral. Let's not put any D's there. E
to the minus the
action. E to the minus the
action. This is the action for a
particular configuration. And here it
is. This is the
action times for each external particle
a factor e to the i k x of z1. Let's say
ZI
KI E factor for each one.
K1 Z1. Yeah. Well, let me not put it for
a moment. E to the I K2 X of Z2 dot dot
dot for each external
particle where Z's are the positions on
the disk where the uh where the momentum
is
injected. This is path integrated. and
then integrated over the
locations where the momenta are
injected. Okay. So you integrate over
everything. Yeah. And the you use the
ikx even though we've already done the
uh the wick rotation. Yeah. Still e to
the i kx. Right. That i is a different
i. You should really write k mu x
mu k
mu x
mu. Okay, there's a k mu for each
component of momentum and an x mu. There
are 26 x's, there are 26 ks and that's
it. That's that's the whole structure of
string theory. question in uh wait okay
the the the momentum is a vector k mu
that's why there's a mu there
okay and and the direction is related to
the x subz no no direction of the
momentum is is the comp here are the
components of the momenta here are the
components of the momenta the x's which
appear there get integrated over they're
part of this path integral here integral
delta x
not part of the Yeah, they could be
since they're in the exponent. You could
consider them to be part of the action
if you like,
you can you can just put them into the
action, but uh you add them you add them
you add them in uh a kx for each
external particle. So, how how does this
when you have the the bandage, you know,
the the the legs can be either swayed or
closed. Does that relate to the X's? How
that's
The shape the shape of the bandage how
the angle of the two legs the angle. No,
no, no, no, no. In this drawing, you
just draw them horizontal. You can draw
it any way you want. Right. It's not in
real space, right? It's not in real
space. It's just a parameter space that
Right. Okay. The amazing thing is that
you can do the
integrals. Everything can be everything
can be done.
uh these are what are called Gaussian
integrals. Everything is quadratic in
the exponent. All the integrals can be
done. That's the good news. The bad news
is you almost always get
infinity. But not if you're in the right
number of dimensions. Now, I am not
going to tell you about the wrong number
of dimensions. I'm going to tell you
what the answer is like in the right
number of dimensions. And it's
incredibly simple.
It's the solution of an electrostatics
problem. It's a solution of an
electrostatics problem. You take every
one of these
X's and think of it as an electrostatic
potential. There are 26 of them or 10 of
them or however many of them there are.
Think of them as separate electrostatics
problems. It's a world now where there
are 26 different kinds of electric
charge. 26 different kinds of electric
field and 26 different kinds of
electrostatic
potentials. The electrostatic potentials
are these x's x1, x2, x3, x4. What do
you think the charges corresponding to
them
are? Can you
guess force? The components of the
momenta in 26 components. The 26
components of the momenta are like 26
kinds of
charges. Each one being the source of
its own electrostatic field. The
electrostatic field being called
X. Okay, here's the here's the
calculation that you do and is it is
really
easy. It
is obtained by doing these integrals.
The
integrals 26 charges. 26, not 26
charges, but 26 different kinds of
charge,
right? 26 different independent kinds of
charge, each creating its own
electrostatic
field. All right, here's what you do.
You take a
disc. This disc is, think of it as a
world in two dimensions.
on this disc you have let's see I get
confused the x
um the
x
yeah the
um boundary conditions are that the
electric that the components of the
electric field perpendicular to the
surface of the disc vanish. It's not so
important the boundary conditions. You
have a dis a world with these 26
different kinds of
electricity. On the boundary you put
charges little charges on the
boundary. At each boundary point there
are 26 charges to put
on. The charges themselves are the
components of the electrostatic
potential are the components of the
momentum. So if this particle comes in
with 26 components of K, those 26
components of K become the
26 charges that you put at that point.
Another 26 charges at that point.
Another 26 charges at that point. And
another 26 charges at that point.
This is a straightforward electrostatics
problem. 26 of them, but it's easy it's
as easy to do 26 of them as it is to do
one of them. Well, in principle, if you
can do an electrostatics problem with
one kind of electric charge, you can do
the same electrostatics problem 26 times
over with different values of the charge
here. All right. So, fixing the values
of the charge and fixing these
points, what do you calculate? You
calculate the electrostatic potential
inside. From that you can calculate the
electric field and once you know the
electric field you can calculate the
electrostatic
energy. You calculate the electrostatic
energy of such a
configuration. That's this whole
integral there. The electrostatic energy
and then you integrate it over the
points. You move the points around, you
integrate over them and that is the
scattering amplitude for the 20 for the
for the 26dimensional particles to
scatter from one set of momenta to
another set of
momenta. So in fact the final upshot is
very easy. It's just an electrostatics
problem with 26 different kinds of
charges. You calculate the electrostatic
energy in here.
Is that one energy or 26 energy? 26.
There are 26 and you add them up. That's
right. There are 26 distinct.
You have 26 potentials. 26 potentials.
26 electric fields.
And you end up ultimately with one
energy, right? One energy. One energy.
And there's no cross terms between the
26. The 26 just operating orthogonally.
There are no cross terms between them.
You take that electrostatic energy. You
exponentiate it. E to the minus the
electrostatic
energy. The whole answer depends on the
positions of the
charges and you integrate it over the
positions of the charges. Okay, you
calculate the electro the 26
electrostatic energies for the 26
different kinds of charges. How do you
do that? You calculate the electric
field. You square the electric field or
you can just calculate the electrostatic
energies if you're uh and you
exponentiate it. You integrate it over
the positions and that gives you the
scattering amplitude for particles whose
components of momenta are the same as
the values of the charges that you put
uh on these points. That's that's the
whole upshot of it. Yeah. The angular
parameter of this
disc has no relation to scattering
angle, right? No, no, no. It has more of
a relationship to the time intervals in
here. Yeah. Yeah. Uh there are various
parameters, but you integrate over them.
You integrate over them and that's the
string theory scattering amplitude. Uh
it's a fairly simple prescription.
Did you say this does not work if it's
not 26?
You got a bunch of infinities from the
path integral which just don't go
away. This is the final answer when it
works. When it doesn't work, it's just
infinite. And uh 26 and
10. So I'm I'm sort of shortcircuiting
it by telling you what the answer is. Uh
it's a it's a very beautiful and simple
uh final
answer. Um but once you know that this
is the procedure, there's nothing to
prevent you from putting lots more
particles
in. You do have to integrate over their
locations on
here. But basically that's the answer
for the scattering of any number of
incoming particles.
The amplitude the thing that you square
the amplitude for any number of incoming
particles to any number of outgoing
particles.
Yeah,
we have three long dimen uh dimensions
in these small ones. So the fact that
you've converted to this Whoa. three
long dimensions. Well, we haven't talked
about compactification yet. We have not.
And uh uh that'll be the next uh that'll
be the next discussion. Yeah, I just
trying to think about that connection to
the potential again. It's because of the
uh coordinates satisfying the applause.
Yes, it's because the coordinates
satisfy the lelass
equation and uh connects you to the
static potential solution. That's right.
The coordinates satisfy well yes they
satisfy the lelass equation and the
lelass equation is the basic equation
for
electrostatics. We didn't have to call
it electrostatics. I could have just
said applause equation with some delta
function sources
here. Uh but it the mathematics is the
same as calculating electrostatics
problem. Um
you have four degrees of freedom for
each of those four points around the
ditch, right? Each angle as an angle and
then you have Yeah, it's actually
simpler than that.
Um, you can use the conformal freedom,
the freedom to reconformally map things
to arbitrarily fix the location of any
three of them. In other words, you
should integrate over all of them. But
for any given configuration, you can
always find a conformal mapping which
will bring this point to here, this
point to here, this point to here, and
then it's only the fourth point for the
case of two in and two out. It's only
the location of the fourth point which
gets integrated from here to here.
That's a technical point. The place the
two points in inside the band the uh
these two point. Yeah. The integral over
these two freedom there, right? No, no,
no. There's really only one integration
which is the time between these two.
They don't have to exactly break apart
in the same the same. Ah, that's a good
point. They could break apart at
different
points like that,
but you can always find a conformal
mapping which will pull pull them back
together. So you have that freedom. You
have that freedom to pull them back
together. So when you add more
points, how does the number of points
map to the number of parameters?
Well, the answer, okay, the answer is
that you have a a a conformal invariance
freedom, a freedom of conformal mapping
that allows you to choose any arbitrary
three points and put them wherever you
like. You fix them. You fix them. Put
the first one here, the second one here,
the third one here, and then all the
other ones get integrated
over. So, the answer is you have n minus
uh n minus3 um uh integrations to do.
Yeah. n minus3 integrations to do.
How does this procedure relate to n
theory? To what? To n theory. Doesn't
yet. Doesn't yet. Not yet. Not yet.
We'll hopefully come to it. The other
diagram that you had where the uh you
had the spooky line going vertical. In
other words, you had the two particles
coming in. That would correspond to if
those two points uh were actually if you
had a negative uh
you want to you want to study it. If you
use a
um coordinates in which it looks like
this and then the other one goes reaches
all further the top one goes further to
the left. Then the integration then the
integration you can pick one of these
you can hold one of them fixed the other
one has to go all the ways to
uh uh from plus infinity to minus
infinity.
I was just comparing to the to the uh to
the uh path the two paths that you you
had that you said were equivalent that
would be equivalent to say the top uh
break the point at the top break being
to the left of the point at the bottom
break. Yeah.
Yep. You do have to do that inte you
have to integrate over but in the
special case where you have them at
exactly the same height the integral
terminates when they touch and it's the
same integral the amazing thing is it's
the same integral and in fact it's the
same integral is integrating over the
points on the boundary of a
disc. So this is a sort of nice uniform
symmetric picture in which all the
particles are on the same footing and
you can pull it and uh you can you know
pull it out and push it in in various
ways to to make it look uh like
different kinds of processes but
it's nice.
Yeah.
So this is open string theory. Open
string theory, the particles are
injected on the boundaries. The
boundaries and these are the edges of
the strings, the end points of the
strings. That's what the boundaries are.
We'll talk about closed string theory a
little bit next
time. Um, so you can see the the
mathematics of it at this level is
fairly simple.
Well, it is. I mean, it's just
electrostatics.
Is
this when you say this is this is basic
restrict theory? Um is this model I mean
this matches up with experimental
results? So with using this formalism
you match what you get when you run some
experiments. Which experiment are you
thinking of?
It's a reasonable description of
hydrons.
Nobody has the vaguest idea what happens
when you collide uh gravitons together.
So I mean we have a good idea, we have
lots of idea but uh the details of it
can you know way beyond us. And there is
a zillion versions of this. Don't get
this is I have described one simple
version of a string theory. There's a
zillion versions and the zillion
versions are connected with the way the
extra dimensions are compactified. We
haven't talked about that.
No, this doesn't agree at all with
experiment. It has 26 dimensions of
space. How could it compare with
experiment?
Terrible out the other end that that
that when you talked about these
scattering amplitudes, you're talking
about something that is they're not
things that you can measure in any
experiment. What I'm trying to figure
out is you're calculating a scattering
amplitude, right? And you're asking
whether it agrees with experiment. The
first thing you would discover if you
did if you uh took these scattering
amplitudes and compared them with
experiment is the number of dimensions
was radically
wrong
immediately. You can't even get started
with it. I
mean we have a lot more to do before we
could make a sensible theory out of this
details. Details
what could be worse? The number of
dimensions of space is
uh let's see there's 25 of them instead
of three. It's uh not it's off by not
even an integer.
Oh, it's better in super string theory
there. The number of dimensions is nine
and it's only three times too large. I
just wanted to get clear that this was
pure mathematics
at the moment. I so does that mean that
eventually we'll come around to a point
where you will compactify these things
and then get reasonable numbers that we
see somewhere on yeah but the compact
the real complexity and enormous
difficulty of this subject the
mathematical sophistication of it is in
the
compactifications and it is really hard
it's where the difficulties are and
um I can show you some simple examples
of compact rectification and I can show
you how they lead
to information about particles and about
gauge groups and things like that. But
to do the real thing is far far not only
beyond me but it's far far beyond the
subject. I mean there's no nobody knows
how to put these things together to make
uh realistic uh theories of
particles.
We're this is a machine for making lots
and lots and lots of different models.
the number of models or the number of
constructions that can be made are in
the 10 to the
thousands.
So this is very much a work in progress.
But on the other hand, there is a very
very definite mathematical subject
uh of constructing such models. They are
highly rigorous and they produce an
enormous wealth of mathematical
information about uh gravity about about
mathematics. But there's no question
that it has not succeeded in giving a
theory of elementary particles or better
yet it has succeeded in giving about 10
to the 500 theories of elementary
particles.
uh which is you know it may be like
that I think it's like that
uh but we will find out this is you know
I I I am not proitizing for this theory
I'm simply telling you what it is is
there a brief description for how we
came about with 26 dimensions in this
model or yeah I yeah there's a brief
description and the unless we talked
about it we talked about 1 plus 2 plus
3+ 4 = - 12 and
uh and uh 12 * 2 is 24 and 24 + 2 is 26.
Remember that.
Are these K's quantized in any sense?
Are they what are they quantized or they
consider continuous value? Which the K
the momenta which things? When you look
at the
electrostatics, do you assume that
there's a quantization or do you assume
there's a continuous value? No. The only
thing that's quantized is the sums of
the squares of the momenta, which is the
mass squared of the particle. Yeah.
Yeah. No, momenta is not quantized. Most
definitely not. Uh, okay. Good.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.